Heat. Heat.
[Music]
Hello, good evening, good day everybody
and welcome to the Askava know this is a
history episode. We're going to talk
about history. I'm going to take
questions that you all have asked in the
comments. We'll do that. But before
that, let's see who is there on the live
chat today. Yes, it's an early episode.
It's an early session. We couldn't do
one yesterday because of various
reasons. So, let's see who is there. I
can see Sugjata is from Singapore. Well,
namaste. Ahilia Patil, hello. Ronit
Kumar, Sep Naik, Bharat Versa, Shashi
Kumar, Vladimir Putin says my
notifications have stopped. Well, I
can't control that. So, uh, well, it is
what it is. Anonymous scientist says,
"Bonjour in congrats for publishing the
brilliant books. Thank you so much. I
appreciate that. Please do read." Uh,
Shriika is there. Tushar Kalpur, Min
Dave, Ammon from Mumbai, Vidi Manar,
Adita Singh, Rat from Pune. Who else do
we have? Satellite, we have Shri
Satellite from Goa with us today.
Abhishek, Kapil Singh, Rishab Shikhar,
Creative Clips, Ammon, Ashwini, Abhinav,
Vishra, Aayush Singh, Pranam, Vikas, PJ,
Amatistic,
Shashi Kumar, Hensi, Penguin, hello
Shash, Sandep, Nyak, good evening,
Ronitkumar, who else? Bharat, Bidori,
Bidori event countdown. Vladimir Putin,
Nabanita Das, team talks, Dharma, who
else? Duv durya duv durya geopolitical
dub from indoor from indor langi sur
uh vikash pj shre vias rohit kalita
vishwa samraat shukla push suri vikash
parata
yes yes yes full books will come
eventually I'm writing books in a
serialized fashion one chapter at a time
each chapter is not small it's
substantial
is saying please launch the book in hard
copy yeah I'll launch it once the book
is complete complete right now I'm
releasing the books the in episodic
format so once the entire set of
episodes is done I will have it
published in hard copy format and yeah
you will be able to get it at that point
in physical form Kevin Shibu progressive
pujan bill Aman how many hours do you
read books daily well it depends I mean
there's no set time a couple of hours
maybe sometimes it's like a whole day
depends and so much more subhhamve
samraat shukla deadly ninja random
Shorts. Hello Kevin Shibu. Aayush Nihal
Nishal Ray Mahishta Cluster
uh Aditia Chili Koti Adue Samarat Kevin
Shibu
feels strong man Sep Nyak Mayank and
everybody else. All right. All right. I
have greeted you all. I will not be able
to greet everyone individually but thank
you so much for being on the live. I can
see Tjas. Hi Tjas. Good to see you sir.
I hope your health is good. Do well sir.
Keep taking care of yourself. pages,
it's good to see you again, one of our
longtime viewers. Very good to see you.
All right. Uh, and so, thank you
everyone for being on the live chat.
Now, let's take some questions. Let's
take some questions. Uh, Aman, you're
very welcome. Rohit doesn't like fiction
books. That's all right. That's okay.
You should go with what you like, sir.
We should go with what you like. Okay.
Let's go and take some questions. I have
a bunch of questions that you all have
asked and I'll take as many as of these
as possible.
Let's go for the first one. This is by
Rahul Dunak. The question is, the
dinosaurs were killed off. Well, the
non-avian dinosaurs were killed off 66
million years ago due to the impact of a
15 km wide roughly meteorite, asteroid,
comet, whatever it was that happened.
The impact was in Yucatan, present day
Yucatan, the Chikshulub impact. So can
we say that some of the megapona like
the stigodon in the Indian subcontinent
became extinct in the pristine epoch by
the lonar crater causing meteorite.
Interesting question. So do we know what
the lonar crater is? I mean many of you
may perhaps not know about it. It's a
it's a significant meteorite crater
meteor crater in India in Maharashtra.
And uh so first of all let's go and find
the lunar lonar crater. Let's go to the
maps. Outstanding. First question itself
brings the maps on the screen. All
right. So we have well let's zoom into
India and let's just search for it. Luna
lake. It's a lake now but it was a
crater. Well let's take a look at the
satellite image. So as you can see it's
a roughly circular thing. Yeah. And this
is located if we zoom out you can see it
is in Maharashtra.
Let's zoom in again. It's a roughly
circular structure right and uh you can
see there are more structures nearby
that seems to be a secondary impact
umber lake and so on. So this is a lake
which is actually a crater and this this
impact event happened about I don't know
50,000 years before today 50,000 55,000
years before today that that sort of
thing. Okay. So, it's a it's a
significant impact crater, not gigantic.
What's the dimensions of this crater?
About a kilometer 1.1 1.2 1.3 km in
diameter if you were considering it to
be an approximate circle. Right? So,
that was the deal. So, this this impact
crater is about 1.2 km wide. The
Chikshul impact crater which is no
longer visible to the untrained naked
eye. The Chichchulub impact crater is
about 200 kilometers in diameter.
Okay. And that was caused by something
like a 10 to 15 kilometer
large asteroid or comet impact. And
that's the event that killed off the
non-avian dinosaurs and it caused a mass
extinction event in event in conjunction
with the decken traps activity volcanic
activity that was happening in in the
decken region of India when India the
Indian subcontinent was at the time in
the middle of the uh Indian Ocean. It it
had still not hit Asia. So the chik
chilob impact crater is about 200
kilometers wide and it caused mass ext
mass extinction on the planet. The lunar
crater is one let's say 1 kilometer
wide. So it's 200 times smaller.
Right? So the the impact impactor the
object that would have struck the earth
at Lodar would be roughly you could say
200 times smaller than the chukul impact
uh object. So if that thing was 15 km
wide let's divide by 10. So that's 1.5
km. Let's divide by 10 again. That's 150
m divide by 2 75 m. So the the object
that would have caused the lunar impact
would have been about 75 m in diameter
or so which is similar to the object the
object that uh caused the Tonguska event
in 1908. The Tunguska event was an it
was not an impact event because the
object exploded in the sky but it caused
a gigantic area of of devastation in in
essentially uninhabited part of Russia.
it leveled enormous you know uh regions
of forest and all that and there are
some some lakes that you find in the
region today that are possibly the cause
the the consequence of that um of that
event. So the so the lonar crater was
probably caused by something similar
to the object that caused the tunguska
event in 1908. And as we know in 1908 it
was pretty devastating locally over
there but it not it did not cause any
any extinction event event. It did not
cause any species to go extinct or any
such thing. So the lunar event would
have been like that. It would have been
pretty pretty big. It would have been
devastating at the time locally. Maybe
over over an area of maybe 500 square
kilm, maybe 1,000 square kilm or maybe a
radius of 500 km around the place where
you have the impact crater but it would
not have been so devastating that it
would have caused uh the extinction of
various megapona or any kind of fauna.
So it would not have done that. Now the
question people will be wondering what
is a stegodon right it's it was an
ancient form of elephant it was an
ancient kind of elephant which used to
live in the subcontinent which existed
in the subcontinent and beyond the
subcontinent so let's quickly take a
look at what the stegodon looked like
okay it was a a kind of elephant steodon
steodon you see this is what a stegodon
looked like and uh this is you could say
an artistic representation it had larger
tusks than present day elephants. And
this animal uh went extinct about around
10,000 or so BC. That's not a whole lot
of time ago. So the Lunar event happened
let's say about 50,000 years before
today. And the Stegodon went extinct
about 12 13 15,000 years before today.
So there's a significant time period
time gap of more than 30,000 years
between the extinction of the stegoon
and the time when the lunar impact event
happens. So clearly these two are not
correlated.
Okay. So that's how you look at it
logically. You look at the time period
of what happened when when the
extinction of this animal happened. It
happened about 10 12 15,000 years before
today. But the Lodar event happened 50
55,000 years before today. So that's a
significant time gap. So that's not
there's no correlation there. And
secondly, the lunar the the object that
would have impacted the earth and
created the lunar crater was way smaller
than the chikulub impactor which was
gigantic, massive. It caused a global
mass extinction event. Right? So uh
yeah. So it it would be incorrect to
think or or or to say that uh the lonar
event was uh responsible for the
extinction of the stegodon or any other
megapona. We have f I mean people have
done some research here and there. in
the Luna region and it it's pretty it's
a pretty significant impact trader but
they found no evidence of that event
having caused any kind of mass
extinction or even localized extinction
events um in the Indian subcontinent.
All right,
second question it's by Napoleon Singh
Shikhawat. Please take my question. I
believe here we have it. Who was the
priest king? Why was this statue given
to Pakistan and why is Mr. Modi
sometimes compared with him.
Okay, let's find out who was the priest
king. Let's put an image on the screen.
Very very iconic, very famous im image,
right? Priest.
Sorry, forgive my spelling. Priest king
priest king. This here image iconic
image that was is of a statue that was
discovered in Mohenadaro. probably
Mohenjaro
and uh very famous image it's one of the
most iconic and most recognizable images
from that time period of our history the
Sarasoti Hindu phase of our history and
this is one figurine of a human being of
a person from that time possibly that
has been discovered and this is for some
reason called the priest king and
there's a lot of speculation as to who
this uh person may or may not have been
okay so that's the priest king so the
first question we have to ask ourselves
is was this individual a priest and a
king?
Was it so? Well, the truth is that we
have absolutely no idea about the
identity of the person that this
figurine may depict. We don't know who
it was. Was it a real person? Was it
just a representation of of a person? We
don't know. Secondly, was he a priest?
We have absolutely no idea.
Was he a king? Well, did we have kings
in those days? If you look at u if you
look at the archaeological evidence that
we have from that time period in
northern western India, the Saraswati
Hindu region, the so-called Indis Valley
uh culture region or Harman culture
region or whatever you want to call it.
If you see uh that time period and the
archaeological record from that from the
time period, you will see that India in
this region gigantic region which is
larger than Egypt and Mesopotamia put
together. So in this region at during
that time 3,000 4,000 5,000 years before
today even
4,000 years before today that time
period big time period at that time
India had by the what's called the
mature Harapan phase become a completely
fully uh um
industrialized civilization and fully
urbanized civilization. We have we had
standardizations of weights
standardization of weights and measures
and we have the same grid layout of
cities and towns and villages everywhere
and we have the same system everywhere
whether it is all the way north in in
Punjab, Hiana even Kashmir all the way
south to to northern Maharashtra
eastwards in Madhya Pradesh or westwards
to the to the border of present day
Persia that entire region you will the
same structure of cities with the same
grid structure cities are well organiz
ized and
you know all of that is there. Civic
amenities are available everywhere that
sort of thing. But what is strikingly
absent is the absolute complete absence
of any palaces of any in of any any
buildings or structures that are you
would associate with powerful figures
with power with kings like palaces or
any such thing. There's no such thing.
There is no building that is more
magnificent than the other buildings.
The biggest and magn supposed supposedly
magnificent buildings were the public
buildings like the public baths and
assembly halls and all that right but
that that those structures served a
civic purpose. It served a purpose that
was uh for all of society. It was not
something that was restricted to a
certain category of of of people from
this time period. So there's the
complete absence of palaces. You can't
see I mean generally when you look at
the archaeological record of any time
period from any part of the world you
will see that yeah you have certain
social structure social stratification
is visible and you can see that there
are forts there are there are palaces
even if they are ruined you can you can
figure out what the social structure
would have been like and what the power
structure would have been like from the
archaeological record
from this time period of Indian history
we find no such evidence it's it's puzz
puzzling who ruled
the people. How was the society
organized? It was clearly fully
industrialized. It was clearly clearly
extremely technologically advanced. It
was clearly extremely well organized and
well planned.
But who ran the whole show? Who are the
administrators? Who are the kings? No
idea. Nothing is visible. Nothing is you
can't make out from the archaeological
record. So clearly it looks like there
was no monarchy or if there was a
monarchy system then the kings lived
very similar to the common people if
there were kings and once again we don't
find any great temples or any such any
such thing from that time period we do
find vic and we find shiblings and all
so our culture was there but you did not
have great temples you did not have
great palaces no such thing so then the
question arises
who does this figure represent? Was it
an important, let's say, politician from
that time period? He does have a great
amount of dignity if you look at the way
he's depicted, right? Or was it a
priest? Well, did we have priests at the
So, the the point I'm trying to make is
that we have no idea how the society was
was run at the time. Did we have priests
who were a higher class? Did we have
kings and royalty or or an aristocracy
that was a higher class?
It doesn't look like that was the case
because there's no evidence of that.
Once again, let me say that the absence
of evidence is not evidence of absence.
Maybe it was done in a very subtle way,
right? The organization of society and
and the administration of society, but
there's no evidence that we can find in
the archaeological record. There were
priests or there were kings. There would
have been priests. But possibly, you
see, one aspect of our culture, of our
civilization, is that our religion, what
we now call Hinduism, is extremely
decentralized.
We don't have any popes. We don't have
any religious leaders as such. Today
these days we have Babas and B what not.
That's a very modern phenomenon. In the
past we had people like Adish
Shankarachara who were extremely
influential but they were influential
not powerful. They did not create this
military structure. I'm at the top and
then I have five lieutenants be below me
and each lieutenant will have 20
lieutenants under them and that sort of
pyramidal structure. We do not have we
do not have that ever. So our religion
was extremely decentralized. So every
home would have a would have a fire
haven place. Every home would possibly
have a shivaling and people would do
their worship on their own without
needing higher guidance from from some
religious leader. So once again the
question is does it then make sense to
call somebody a priest?
Does it make sense to call someone a
king? The Greeks had this ideal, you
know, that they had this ideal of the
philosopher king that the most
enlightened kings are philosopher kings
who are not just kings who hold power,
but they're also extremely wise people,
philosopher like people, that sort of
thing. Maybe that has been transposed
upon this figure and that's why it's
called the priest king. I'm not sure who
coined this term priest king, right? But
there is no evidence that this person
was a priest. There is no evidence that
this person was a king. We don't even
know who the person was. If it indeed
depicts a real fe a real person from
history. Maybe it does. Probably it
does. Maybe it was a very popular
person. Maybe it was a person who was of
great importance to society. We don't
know for sure. So the so the gist of my
answer is that we have absolutely no
idea who this represents. What was the
person's name? What did what did he do?
What was his function in society? During
what time period did this person live?
if he did live and so on. So that's
about the priest king. It's a huge
mystery. We don't know who it was. Why
was this statue given to Pakistan? Well,
don't ask me. I have no idea why the
statue was given to Pakistan. It was
discovered in the what 1920s 30s
whenever it was discovered before the
partition and you know destruction of
India and it was for a long time in a
museum in Delhi I believe and after the
um 71 war when India for some reason
became again friendly with Pakistan
that's when the Zulfi Ali said that give
us the figure of the priest king and
give us the figure of the dancing girl
it's another very iconic statueette that
we have of a dancing world and it looks
like we only gave one which was the
priest king and now it is in Karachi
somewhere in some museum in Karachi why
did we have to give it to the Pakistanis
I have no idea what was the need for
that why do you have to make these
unilateral concessions to a defeated
country right and they don't even
believe in this this culture anymore the
Pakistanis so why did they want it why
did we give it back why did we give it
not give it back it was it is ours
anyway even if it it may have been
discovered in Harap Mohendra wherever it
was which is currently in Pakistan
temporarily but it it belongs to our
civilization our culture not the not the
culture and whatever the Pakistanis
espoused today right so that's a
political it was a political decision to
give the priest king to the Pakistanis
and that's where the statue is today why
is Mr. Modi compared to him well look at
the face
it's a very similar face right Mr. Modi
does resemble
the person depicted in this uh statue
and this figure. So that's why people
compare Mr. Modi with him. I think I may
have also been to some extent a a
causative figure in this comparison
because many years ago I think 21 or
something I had put out a short video
about something and I had it was about
did the Indis Valley civilization die
away. That was the the the answer the
question that that I'd answered in the
short clip and in the in the thumbnail I
had put an image of the priest king
so-called priest king and an image of
Mr. Modi and you and you can see clearly
so so much resemblance right so really
it did die out we the same people we the
descendants of the same people of of the
people who lived during that time that's
the deal so maybe that's why Mr. Mr.
Modi is compared with him because people
imagine that this the person depicted in
the figure is perhaps a king a great
king from from our ancient history and
Mr. Modi somehow has those
characteristics and facial uh the facial
features are very similar. So that's why
Okay.
Okay. Real Vladimir Putin is here and
the question is do you think that the
painter's biggest mistake was attacking
the USSR? If the painter didn't attack
the USSR then the axis may have won. So
and and if so what would the world have
looked like as a consequence of such a
decision and what have what would have
been the impact on India? So the painter
obviously refers to the Austrian painter
which is Adolf Hitler who who who wanted
to be a painter and yeah that's that's a
whole different story from a from a
certain period of his life. Uh was his
biggest mistake attacking the USSR
probably probably operation Barbarosa.
So the Soviets and the and the and the
Nazis the the two governments had this
non-aggression pact the molotov ribbon
throp pact right that we will not attack
each other and we will uh we the two
nations had an understanding of how
various uh subjugated nations would
their territories would be divided up up
divided up and so on. So there was this
non-aggression pact between the USSR and
Nazi Germany and uh if if let's say
Hitler had not attacked the USSR started
operation Barbarosa then maybe he would
have been able to focus on England on on
on Britain and maybe he would have been
able to conquer Britain that's a
possibility and maybe he would have had
more success in North Africa and
whatever else he was doing through Raml
and his campaign the desert fox's
campaign in North Africa and so on and
obviously that would and if he had not
attacked the USSR then the whole might
of the USSR eventually would not have
been unleashed on Nazi Germany because
80% of the winning in second world war
was done by the Soviets not by the
Americans the Americans entered the war
at a much later period in the war okay
so it was the Soviets who did the
fighting the dying and the winning and
the Americans now because of Hollywood
they portrayed themselves as the as the
greatest victors of the second world war
the consequence the the new world order
that came as a consequence it it saw the
ascendance of the US of the USA and it
became the most powerful nation sure but
the second world war was won by the
Soviets 80% of it not in the European
theater in the western theater not by
the Americans so if the painter had
decided not to attack the USSR what
could have happened then you would you
would probably have had a situation
where the painter would have conquered
Brit Britain and uh maybe he if if that
would have happened he would have also
captured much of North Africa the that
desert fox campaign that was going on
maybe he would have taken Suis and taken
the Suez Canal in that case if the
non-aggression pact had held right and
then what would have been the situation
like it would have been a a situation
like what you have in Europe today you
have western Europe which is dominated
by dominated by NATO and you have the
eastern European countries that are that
are uh part of the Soviet block. I mean
today many of the Eastern European
countries are also part of NATO. So
essentially it's the Russians standing
alone against everyone in Europe apart
from a couple of countries like Belarus
and so on. Latia, Lithuania, Estonia,
these are part of essentially the NATO
block or EU block and all the former
Soviet uh satellite states are you could
say now allies or vasals of the
Americans.
So if Hitler had not attacked the USSR,
maybe that sort of situation would have
happened that you would have a bunch of
nations that are under Soviet domination
and the rest of Europe would have been
under Nazi occupation. That's what would
have happened. And if the painter had
would have conquered the UK, then India
would have been liberated,
right? then the the connection between
the u British occupiers in India and
their overlords in the UK would have
been severe. It would have been cut it
would have been cut off and all the
supplies and whatnot and the leadership
and whatever else
was provided from the UK would not have
happened. So that would have led that
would have probably led to the overthrow
and all the all the puppets of the
British Raj the various politicians who
to whom power was eventually handed over
in 1947 they would have lost power
because their power came from from the
overlordship of the British I'll not
take any names because that would be
controversial. So India would have been
liberated then and the politicians who
came to power in 4750 wherever they
would probably not have come to power.
It would have been a clean liberation of
India and maybe India would have
reverted to a civilizational status
which it currently doesn't have. So it
would have been a major
major change. It would it would have had
a major impact on India. A very positive
impact on India actually. Yeah. That's
how the world works. You see cause and
effect.
Nirvana Shanks says, "What no why is the
Rosetta Stone so important and how did
it help understand Egyptian writing? The
Rosetta Stone, Egyptian heroglyphics. So
the Egyptian script was not understood
for a very long time, right? I mean the
Egyptians understood it but then
Egyptian culture and civilization was
wiped out, right? Nothing persists to
the day until today. nothing at all from
the old Egyptian civilization and
culture. Nothing exists today
culturally. Right? So Egypt's culture
disappeared. It was destroyed. And for
the longest time, for a period of more
than about 15,700 years, almost 2,000
years, let's say, people did not know
how to read the Egyptian inscriptions,
the heroglyphics.
And once the west became dominant and
they capt they subjugated Egypt in other
countries, they were their historians
were fascinated with this Egyptian
writing. So they wanted to understand
what's written but they had no way of
deciphering the script and then this
stone was discovered. Let's let's look
take a look at what this stone looks
like. It's an inscription in three
different scripts. Okay, Rosetta stone.
What's it look like? We'll look at an
image.
So this is the Rosetta stone. Okay, you
can see there are three sections top,
middle, and bottom. And the three
sections are written. It's the same
message essentially the same message
that is written in three different
scripts.
So which scripts is is is this message
written in? One was the Egyptian
heroglyphic script. The second was the
Egyptian demotic script and the third
was Greek
because this uh inscription was made the
Rosetta stone was made around 30 300 BC
or some around that time around that
time when Egypt was ruled by the Greeks
because of the uh effects of the of the
conquest of Egypt by Alexander.
So Egypt was ruled by the Tlemic dynasty
and this Rosetta stone inscription is in
is the same message in three different
scripts. the herographic script, the
demotic script and Greek. Now Greek was
understood to the western historians. So
then this started the process. Okay, now
we have three scripts and we have the
same message essentially. So let's try
and now figure out. So slowly various
historians various linguists worked on
it and over a period of time they
started cracking the script. So one of
the ways of doing it is you find the
names of kings in a script you
understand right and if it's repeated
two three times you look at you look for
certain similar patterns in the scripts
you don't understand and then you try
and then you know what the name of the
king sounds when you write in Greek now
you find the same repeated patterns in
the other scripts then it means it has
the same sound so then you can
understand what those two three
characters what what the sounds of those
two three characters mean so you can
assign sounds to the characters and
that's how you start working backwards
and forwards and whichever way and
eventually you can you can uh decipher
the script. So that's how it was done
and uh that's how it uh helped
historians finally decipher the
heroglyphic script.
Magnificent Shri Nehuji says when we say
Indo-Uropean languages what does it
really mean in Bat? We have our
languages which are you could say upper
branch forms of mother Sanskrit
corrupted forms of mother tanskrit and
we understand u much of our language
like people from the south will get an
idea of punjabi people from Bengal
understand marati gujati hindi marati
Bengali almost the same here and there
with some differences yep we do
understand that yeah so what's the deal
with the European languages because we
don't understand a word of them even
though we say that these are part of the
indo-uropean language family we use the
term Indo-uropean languages I am sure
people of Europe will understand in some
multiple languages here and there. So is
this Euro Indo-Uropean language family a
complete figment of imagination? Is it
fiction or is it really a thing? Very
good question you asked. So in India we
understand each other's languages u it's
u I mean look even if someone speaks
Tamil or if someone speaks Malali or
someone speaks Canada they will still be
able to understand a lot of words from
the northern languages and and so on. So
because of because of the way the
languages are and because of our because
of thousands and tens and thousands of
years of Indian history and when it
comes to the what's called the Aian
languages or Indo-arian languages well
they are very mutually intelligible if
you speak any for example Bengali you
will be able to understand much of what
someone says in Hindi or Gujarati or
Marathi or Punjabi or whatever and so on
very mutually intelligible with some
changes but you can understand what
someone is saying. Similarly, in Europe,
if someone speaks, let's say, Spanish,
they'll be able to figure out what an
Italian person is saying to some extent,
right? The Ramos languages, if someone
speaks, let's say, German, they'll be
able to understand what a Dutch person
is speaking to some extent. Or if
someone speaks English, they may be able
to figure out what a German person is
saying because of certain words that are
kind of common. But when it comes to
Indian languages and European languages,
I mean you really can't understand each
other's languages, right? And then
there's the case of Persian. So if you
pay attention to Persian, if someone
speaks Persian slowly, you you will even
be able to understand some Persian
because the Persian is way way more
similar, way closer to the Indian
languages than to the Western languages,
European languages. Now, so the question
is, is what is this thing? Is this a
truth? Is this a real thing? The
Indo-Uropean language family or is it
just fiction? So, let it's it's true.
These these languages are part of the
same language family. And let me show
you why. So, let's see. Okay. Um,
Indo Indo
European
language
similar words. Okay. Mother, father,
sister, day, night, etc. I'm going to
show you the similarities. Indo-Uropean
vocabulary.
Where do we go? Indo-Uropean common
words of Indo-Uropean language. Let's
see this website. Okay. I have not seen
it before. Do we have Okay, here we have
it. Mother, father. Okay, so
mama means me. In Greek, it's ma. In
Latin, it's me. In English, it's me.
Tu means you. It is Greek. In Greek,
it's su. And tum in Latin becomes to in
English it becomes thw
similar then par in Sanskrit we say par
pru right that's father in Greek it
becomes per in Latin it becomes per in
English becomes father and so on matter
in Sanskrit is mother obviously which
becomes matter in Greek matter in Latin
and mother in English brother in
Sanskrit becomes frater in Latin
and brother in English. Swashtar or
swastri in Sanskrit becomes soror in
Latin and sister in English. Dhitar
which is daughter becomes daughter in
English and tugar in in Greek.
Ashwas becomes hippos inquas in and so
much more. Janu means ni. It's the same
word in French janu which is janu in
Sanskrit. Uh I mean there's so many
examples of this you know septa is seven
which is hap hapta in in Greek it's also
it's it's in Latin and seven in English
ashta becomes octo octo 8 na becomes no
or nine dasa becomes da in Greek and
desm in Latin shatam becomes hecton
centm 100 indo-uropean europ indo-anian
words it's even closer. Okay. Sanskrit
in English, Mata becomes mother, pithar
becomes father, brhar becomes brother
and so much more. So much more. There
there's so many similarities. If you
look slightly below the surface, if you
do a surface level analysis just on the
bas basis of how languages sound, you
won't see any similarities. But if you
do a deeper analysis, you'll see
shocking similarities emerge all over
the place. All over the place. Um when
it comes to the days of the week. Okay.
In in in Sanskrit we have what? Raviar,
Sumoir, Mangalwar, Buddha, Guru,
Shukrash, Shani.
Now, Raviar. Ravi. Who is Ravi? Ravi
means the sun. Raviar becomes Sunday.
Yes. Okay. Sar Monday, right? Who what
is S? Sar. What is Som? S means moon,
which is Monday. In French, it's learn.
Lun means moon. Once again the same
pattern. Uh so mangal mangal is mars
in French you have mai which is Tuesday
and Tuesday in English is from tier t y
r it's a Nordic god
then wens day mangal bud
bud it's mercury right in French you say
mehi mercury Thursday is what mal guru
guru right guru is It is it is Jupiter.
Guru is Jupiter. Jupiter. Who was
Jupiter?
Who was Jupiter?
Well,
it was Indra. Indra became Zeus. Zeus
became Jupiter. Jupiter became Thor. Why
is it called Thor's day?
And so on. I can give you the whole
thing. The similarities in language,
culture are striking. They're
unmistakable.
But you need something beyond that goes
deeper than surface level analysis. Then
you will see the shocking patterns
emerge everywhere. So it tells you that
this was all part of one culture long
long ago which originated somewhere and
the question is where and the white
supremacists will claim that it all
originated in white Europe which is
utter nonsense. All right. Okay.
Nirvana Shanks says, "Who were the
janiseries in the Ottoman Empire and how
did they go from useful soldiers to
causing problems?" The Janiseries in the
Ottoman Empire. The Janiseries is a very
well bloody period of history. So it was
like this. See, first of all, let's take
a look at the region we talking about
and then we will uh go into a slightly
more detail. Let's put the map on the
screen. We're talking about Turkey,
right? So Turkey a thousand years ago,
there was no no Turkish person there. No
one spoke Turkish or practice Islam,
right? So what happened is about 11
around 11, 1200 AD, the Turks were
fleeing from the Mongols. The Turks used
to live in Central Asia. Central Asia,
Kazakhstan, Tajakistan, not Tajakistan.
Okay, not Tajak. Kazakhstan, Usbakistan,
Kyrgystan, Turk Manistan, all those
stands, not the Indo Iranian stan which
is Tajakistan, the other stance and all
of that. Okay. So the Turks lived in
this region also in southern Russia. The
Tatars were also Turks and then the
Mongol Empire erupted out of nowhere and
the Turks fled from the Mongols because
the Mongols were an allconquering power
and the Turks were frightened. So they
fled, they fled, they fled westwards and
they came in the region between the
Black Sea and the Caspian Sea and they
went southwards and that's how they
entered Anatolia.
Anatolia is the major portion of Turkey,
the Asiatic portion of Turkey. So they
the Turks entered this region and they
were well they were nomads used to
fighting all the time and they found
this population of peaceful Greek
people, civilized Greek people and they
smashed this population and they took
the land and the they enslaved the
people of of the Greek origin people and
then they you know perpetrated the
standic standard the standard Turkish
atrocities and all conversion by force
and uh you know thieving
kidnapping women and forcibly marrying
them to Turks and that sort of thing.
And that's how the Turks became white
people, essentially Greek people. If you
look at the genetics of Turkey, it's
it's Greek genetics or some and some
Armenian genetics. That's it. Very
little Turk genetics. So they um they
essentially enslaved the local people
and forced their women to marry Turks
over and over again over God knows how
many generations. And that's what
happened. Now the Ottoman Empire then
with the conquest of Constantinople 1453
it became a thing and then they became a
powerful force and they were an
expansionist force. They expanded
westwards, eastwards and so on. They
conquered the the Baltic regions and
they enslaved the people there and one
of the means of of subjugating these uh
defeated populations was to extract what
was called the blood tax.
The blood tax. So every village they
will go to every village and they'll
they'll say that uh every year you will
give us x number of boys young boys like
less than 10 years old. You will give
your young boys to us. Every village
needs has a certain kota. Every year
they need to provide a certain number of
boys. Maybe it's 10 boys. Maybe it's 20
boys. Whatever it is and these boys
would be taken by force from their
families. There's nothing the families
could do. The boys would be taken under
the tutilage of the Turks. They would be
converted to Islam, circumcised, all
that and then they would be turned into
soldiers and the indoctrination
brainwashing was so thorough that they
became this the strongest the most
powerful fighting force of the Turks the
elite fighting force the janiseries
right eventually they became so powerful
that they caused political problems and
they they you know that that's how power
works so that was the deal it was the
devir system or something it's called
the blood tax system horrific thing that
they did they
steal boys from the local people and
then use those boys after they grow up
to oppress the locals because by the
time they're fully Islamized and
Turkishized and then they would oppress
their own people, their own families,
their own villages and cities and
countries, that's what they would do.
Horrific. Well, that's part of Turkish
history and culture. The system of the
janiseries, the blood tax.
Vashishta says how did the parliament
come into existence in Britain and when
did it power become more than that of
the British crown the king or the queen
how did that happen right interesting
question
so historically before the Normans
conquered England in 1066 AD there was
no parliament or or any such thing uh
before the Normans you had the
Anglo-Saxons the angles and the Saxons
who uh ruled over these islands the
British islands and they had a system
they had kings obviously and the kings
would have a a council of advisers which
was called the whiten whiten gamut was
the meeting of the council of the king
that sort of thing and that's where the
real power lay the king and and their
council of advisers then once the
normans took over when William the
conqueror conquered England in the year
1066 AD he smashed the existing system
destroyed it uh and replaced it with a
Norman system and uh in which which
eventually became what England is today,
what what Britain is today. So the king
William and his descendants for some for
a couple of centuries they would have uh
council of advisers themselves which was
called I don't remember what it was
called in Latin and that's where the
power lay but eventually uh by the 13th
century or something some kind of
parliament had had uh had uh emerged
which was essentially the powerful
people they would be brought together in
one place so that they could decide
about the important things of the of of
the country. So it would be uh priests
which are cardinals and all that and
there would be some wealthy land owners
and and the nobles. So that was the kind
of parliament you had. It was all
entitled privileged people and they they
would come and decide about minor
affairs in the country and they would
you know maybe make some decisions that
would have some impact at a low level in
the country. Then over time the
parliament became a more established
thing and then you would have the then
eventually you had a house of lords and
a house house of commons. The lords were
the old parliament, the priests and the
aristocrats and the landed nobles. All
of those people those are the lords and
then you had a house of commons which
was which was the common people who had
no nobility or any such thing no
privilege and they also would send
people and that's how the parliament was
was divided into two uh two houses the
house of lords and the house of uh the
commons and eventually and slowly over
time the parliament became slightly
gradually over time see more more
consequential slightly more powerful
over time uh by the 14th 15th century
the the parliament had
significant control over uh taxation
possibly and uh taxation taxation and
legislation right but the power the
ultimate power obviously lay in the in
the crown the king
it's then there was a revolution so then
the parliament obviously the nature of
power is that you want more and more
power so there was a revolution in 1688.
1688 if I'm not mistaken. It was called
the Glorious Revolution. Let's let's
fact check my year. Do I have do I
remember it correctly? Was it a the
glorious thing in 168? Glorious
reolution
16. Yeah. 1688. There was a glorious
revolution in 1688 which which saw the
deposition of uh these kings James and
all and different different uh I think
it was a woman who came to power who was
put in power who was a relative of James
and her husband was a foreigner I don't
remember the specific details you can
look it up and that's where parliament
becomes more powerful than than the king
and uh then then the king becomes a kind
of a figurehead it So after the glorious
revolution, England, Britain became a
constitutional monarchy in which the
king would
give his rubber stamp approval to
whatever parliament said and the king
could not function without parliament
support that sort of thing. Uh so that
that caused a different kind of
equilibrium and today it is said that
the monarchy is just a set of
figureheads and they don't they clearly
don't really have any real power but
they still are extremely wealthy. So
that's how it happened. It's a very
gradual process that took roughly a
thousand years maybe 800 years that sort
of thing. So that's how the power
structure evolved in England and in
Britain over a period of about 8 n
centuries. So yeah.
Okay. Aayush says please tell us in
detail about Rajputs. How Rajuts
contained the Mughals and what
sacrifices they made in doing so. Look
the Rajputs
Muggals was a much later period. When
did Baba in uh invade? When did Baba
arrive in India? Let's uh let's find
this. Baba was the first muggle, right?
Wasn't he? Babber India. When did he
founder of the Muggal Empire? He w he
when did he come to power? Which year?
Let's quickly reference this
untrustworthy source. Okay. 1526.
1526 is when Baba becomes uh king of a
small part in a small region in northern
India, right? 1526.
But the Turk and Arabic invasions
started happening in the 700s
in the 8th century. That's a full seven
centuries before the muggles become the
power in India. Right? And all these
centuries, seven centuries, the Turks
were trying their best to invade and
occupy India.
The first part of India to fall to the
Turks was Gandhar which is now called
Afghanistan, right? And it's the
original Kashmir. What happened there,
you saw later happen in Kashmir and
other parts of India.
So the Turks launched wave after wave
after wave after wave of invasion of
India and they got some footholds here
and there. They took Gandhar. Yes. And
from there they would then they used
Gandhar as the launch pad for launching
further invasions into India. The Gores
and Gaznavis and all they came from
Gandhar right which was turned into
Afghanistan. And who fought? It was the
Indian kings and kingdoms of that time.
So if you look at the 7th century, 8th
century, 10th century, 11th century, the
term Rajput did not exist.
This term came into existence much
later.
It's interesting. It would be
interesting for historians to look at
when does this term first appear in the
historical record or Rajput or
Rajaputra.
Right?
So when we say Rajput today we are
referring to the kingdoms and the kings
of those times the the monarchies of
those times from the 8th century to the
14th 15th 16th whatever century and who
were these Rajput they did not call
themselves Rajput at the time right so
who were these what we call Rajputs
today who were these people these were
the ancient ruling dynasties of India
dating back to the late Vic age so they
they were in charge of ruling various
parts of India you had kingdoms. There
were times when the whole of the
subcontinent was united under a single
emperor, a single empire and there were
times of fragmentation which is what was
the case when the Turks started started
invading India. Um so the Rajputs who we
know now called the Rajputs were the
Chawans and all the various u not just
the Cha so many so many famous surnames
as we know all these kingdoms they
fought but the problem was that they
they were separated they were not under
a single unified command like what you
have in an empire so they all fought
they made tremendous sacrifices they
repelled the Turks you know we talk
about the Hunik invasions because it's
not it is not controversial right there
were there was there Wave after wave
after wave of Hunik invasions of India,
the Huns tried their best to invade
India for like two centuries and once
again Gandhar was the first part of
India to fall to the Huns. Okay. And it
was the Gupta emperors who repulsed the
Hunik invasions especially Scandupta. He
spent his whole life fighting uh you
know fighting of the Hoons and
eventually after his death the Hoons
were able to you know capture
significant portions of India and
settled down and they became Indians of
course. So the Hunik invasion period
took like two three centuries. The Turk
invasions that went on for seven
centuries before they made actual
progress
real progress and in the form of the
Muggal Empire. Right? So that seven
centuries of resistance was done by the
Rajputs but you will not find any any of
this
given in any form of any sort of detail
in your textbooks because then you will
kind of be proud of your country right
but we we are supposed to be portrayed
as a country of losers that's why our
history textbooks only talk about the
glories of Baba and all whatnot this
little chieftain who came from and John
and Usbakistan
but all the centuries of of
of resistance to the Turks. Very little
is mentioned. Baba Raul, he's a kind of
semi-leendary, semi-th mythical person
in the imagination of lots of Indians.
Most most Indians probably don't even
know Paparal existed and what he did and
he he reconquered many parts of what is
today Pakistan from the Turks. But
eventually he also passed away and
things went the way it is. So the the
the resistance was fierce. It was
centuries of resistance. Tremendous
sacrifices were made and eventually the
Rajputs the Rajput kingdoms of the later
period like 16th century 17th century
they were vasalized by the muggles. And
that's why lots of people like to say
that the Rajputs you know they they they
became what allies of the muggals. Let
me tell you something what happened
after 1857.
Everyone was vasalized by the British,
right? But nobody taunts those. Nobody
taunts those princely states and their
kings whose descendants still live among
us today. Nobody taunts them today. They
also you could say sold their country
because you would if if if becoming a
vasal means you sold your country off.
Well, what the hell happened there? You
see when the when the oppressive when
the occupying powers force is
overwhelming
then this sort of thing happens.
So eventually after seven eight
centuries of resistance the Raj portuts
eventually became vasalized by by
Jalaluduin
right Jalaludin what what's his name
Akbar Jalaluduin that sort of thing but
the sacrifices were immense and the the
the toll that they paid were was
horrific horrific
and yeah so that's the deal but this
poor this this period of Indian history
is not u examined by historians
And there's very little of of it in your
textbooks and that's why all these
various misinterpretations exist about
the Rajbuts.
Nirvana Shanks says what was the typing
rebellion and what beliefs of Hong Kuan
started it? Hong Yukuan.
The typing rebellion I mean China has
these horrifying civil wars where 20 30
million people will die just just like
that. The typing rebellion starts around
1850 or something. You can look up the
exact dates yourself if you want are
interested. Around 1850 the typing
rebellion starts and it went on until
about 1865 about 14 15 years it went on
and the death toll was in excess of 20
million. So what was the deal? So the
rebellion the the the leader of the
rebellion was this individual called
Hong Kuan
and he aspired to become a high-ranking
Chinese bureaucrat and the in the
Chinese used to have this examination
system. So you to sit for the exam it's
a very very comprehensive exam and it's
very hard to pass very difficult to very
difficult to crack the exam and I think
this guy he tried two three times and he
failed every time and he eventually
became disenchanted disillusioned and
then he developed delusions of grandeur.
So he declared that I am the younger
brother of Jesus Christ and he became a
and he started propounding you know
propounding a new religion which is
which was apparently a combination of
Christianity with some local Chinese
beliefs and he said that the Chinese
society needs to be reformed and uh land
and wealth needs to be redistributed
among the poor. Very very nice thing to
say. It was like kind of a communist
propaganda kind of thing. And he amassed
a lot of followers and he wanted to
overthrow the the government of the the
theQing
Empire, theQing dynasty. Uh and he
wanted to to overthrow Confucianism, the
the belief system, which is an atheistic
belief system in China and Buddhism,
whatever. and he wanted to replace it
with his weird form of religion which
was Christianity mixed with some some
other beliefs whatever I don't know what
whatever it was. So this was the attempt
to impose Christianity on China and
because of his uh of of his uh what he
said that the land and wealth needs to
be distributed that sort of thing if I
come to power I'll do it that's why he
amassed a lot of followers and a
significant part of uh south eastern
China came under this guy's dominion
Hong Huan and obviously the the empire
will not tolerate that so that that
caused a war between the two factions
between the empire and uh the the forces
of Hong Xi Shiu Kuan and this this war
the civil war went on for about 10 14 15
years and it caused tremendous suffering
famine massacres what not all of that
the total death toll is in excess
probably of 20 million and uh yeah so
eventually Hong Shuan was whether he
committed suicide or killed or whatever
but he died and his son also was was
dealt with and this was ended. So that
was a typing rebellion in very short. It
was a disaster for China. It caused
tremendous well structural and other
issues. It significantly weakened
theqing empire
and then you had another uh rebellion
another revolt. Let's let's discuss
that.
So Yajnavalia says, "What were the
causes of the Dongan revolt 1862 to 1877
in China that occurred against theQing
dynasty? How did Zhong managed to
suppress this revolt?" So Jehong Tang
was the theQing Empire's principal
general who fought against the the the
people who who caused the revolt. What
was this Dongan revolt? So you have the
typing rebellion that is now in its last
phase and then you have a dungan revolt
that starts. The typing rebellion was in
the southeast of China. The dungan
revolt was in the northwest of China.
Totally different like diametrically
opposite places. Right? The dungan
revolt is also called the hoi muslim
rebellion.
It was the attempt by Muslims in present
day and also other provinces. Zing Jang
came in later. Other provinces of China,
eastern, sorry, western provinces,
northern western provinces of China, the
Muslims who lived there, they wanted to
establish a new empire there, right? And
it all started with massacres of
Hanchinese by the by the Hui Muslims. So
the Hoi Muslims started this revolt
against the country, against the the
empire. They started by massacring lots
and lots of Hanchinese civilians. And
then the Han Chinese started, you know,
organizing and they fought back and
that's how the whole revolt started and
there were suspicions that the typing
rebellion had a role the rebels of the
typing rebellion the leaders possibly
may have had a role in assisting the hoi
Muslims who were revoling also at by
1862 so they wanted to create a separate
amirat or or kingdom carved out of
Chinese territory and that's what was
the cause of the Dongan revolt or Hoi
Muslim revolt and uh
Shu Jong Tang he well he played a
sophisticated game obviously he did use
military force very powerful very
organized military force he had a very
he had a pretty modernized military for
for that time very well organized very
disciplined very professional so he took
that into the battlefield against on
very on lots of occasions lots of
battles happened against as the Hoi
Muslims and he crushed them. But he also
played a political game in which he
would he gave some inducements to some
factions of the Hoi Muslims to come on
the Chinese side and they would be
elevated to high positions and given
various inducements. So by that game of
divide and rule that strategy he was
able to weaken the the the
rebellion and eventually he was able to
defeat it militarily. Once again
tremendous death toll I don't know 10 20
million very easily that that sort of
death toll happened and uh entire
provinces were like 60 70% depopulated
because of this uh yeah so that was so
the so the Chinese faced two rebellions
one after the other I mean there was a
period where both were happening at the
same time and this caused great amount
of weakening of the chin empire which
eventually fell around what 1911 or
thing.
Okay, two questions about the same topic
essentially. Aush says, "Why didn't we
lose our polytheism despite we as an
India despite being under a millennium
of foreign occupation and those
barbarians tried their best to do it
after reading the darkening age?" Well,
kudos you read the darkening age. All
right, it's a book I have recommended on
multiple occasions. So after reading the
darkening age I discovered that Europe
lost its majority culture in just four
centuries the old Indo-Uropean culture
and that too didn't happen with any very
glorious resistance. So the resistance
from Europe was not that significant and
in in a matter of four centuries the
Indo-Uropean religion was wiped out the
culture was wiped out and superimposed
with Christianity. Christianity became
the dominant religion. It was forced
onto Europe. And Amisha says why was
Christianity so successful in
eradicating the indigenous religious
traditions of Europe. So essentially we
need to contrast what happened in Europe
with what happened in India. So in
Europe you had the very rapid
Christianization of Europe a complete
destruction of the indigenous um culture
and belief systems. And in India you had
a thousand years of foreign occupation
in various parts of India. It's not like
for a thousand years the whole of India
was under foreign occupation but over
time it was a creeping creeping thing.
The it was a creeping advance of foreign
occupiers. It starts with Gandhar and
that then it goes further eastwards and
southwards and eventually you have the
Muggal Empire during orex time that
which conquered much of the subcontinent
and then you have the Europeans who came
in. So eventually the the Muggal Empire
was destroyed by the Maratas, the great
Maratas who liberated India from the
Turks but the Maratas themselves had
their their empire did not last very
long because of various political
reasons infighting and all that and the
British took advantage of that and they
created the British Raj and so on right
so India was under the British under
British occupation for about two and a
half centuries and we were under Turk
occupation various parts of India for
about I don't know 7 8 centuries right
that sort of thing various parts of
India if you include Gandhar.
So
why were the occupiers of India, foreign
occupiers, the Abrahamic occupiers of
India, why were they not able to destroy
our polytheistic
uh culture and civilization? It still
exists in some shape or form. But Europe
it happened so fast. What what was the
diff what was the reason? Why did it
happen so easily in Europe? In Persia
also
but not in India. What was the deal?
So you see it's like this.
It's like this. In Europe,
the kings themselves
became Christians and then they forced
their people to become Christian because
they saw Christianity as something that
will uh strengthen them strengthen their
hold on power because now it's just one
militarized structure of of priests that
that control the religion as opposed to
a completely decentralized religion that
you had. So in Europe one after the
other various kings and emperors started
adopting Christianity and because they
control
power which means they they have the
monopoly in violence that's why they
were able to subjugate the people very
rapidly
and the the church was a very powerful
force in that sense and they employed
all kinds of brutal tactics. So you have
kings like Charlean who launched the
northern crusades
which is brutalization of the people and
and forcing them to to give up their
religion and adopt Christianity that
sort of thing. So in Europe you had
kings and emperors who themselves became
Christian and then forced it down the
throats of the populations happened over
a period of time like you say it's four
centuries.
Uh so once you
you do a coup essentially at the very
top then it's very easy to do it to to
projected project it downwards. The same
thing happened in Persia also. Kings
very rapidly became Islamic and that's
how Persia also very quickly uh the
population was made to adopt Islam to to
convert to Islam. Most of the population
when it comes to India the kings never
became
you know they never converted to foreign
religions. The kings kept on fighting.
We speak about the Rajput resistance
which I took two three questions ago.
Well, if those Rajput kings from the 8th
century to the 15th century, if they had
decided that let's convert to the
religion that the Turks have brought and
and let's
you know force our population to to
convert too, it would have happened very
rapidly.
Understand that. But the the kings
themselves decided that we will not give
up our culture. We'll fight and we'll
die if required. And that's why there
was that's why it did not succeed. Once
again when the British occupied India
they brought in their legions of
missionaries right but even though a lot
after 1857 every single king every
single Indian kingdom became vasalized.
Every Indian kingdom became vasalized
after 1857 but not a single king or
queen converted to Christianity
as far as we know. There may have been
some some crypto converts here and there
possibly. I'm not sure.
But the overwhelming majority of our
kings and queens did not convert to
Christianity despite the European
despite the British having brought in
millions of not millions but legions of
missionaries with the express purpose of
converting Indians right so because of
this resistance from India because our
culture our religion of our civilization
is so deep rooted it's thousands tens of
thousands of years old we have had the
say an evolving form of the same culture
since about what 80 thou 80 80,000 years
before today essentially
It's so deeprooted that's why it it
could not work. But today you will see
that if the same efforts continue today
we don't have kings right but we have
politicians.
Now do you know of any politicians who
have
converted
or converts
even crypto converts and they are
pushing the agenda top to bottom. It
happens. It works when the push comes
from the top and it goes downwards
because the entire might of the state
apparatus is used to convert.
Right? So as long as we had kings in
India, even if it was vasalized kings
under the British or for some time under
the Muggal Empire, even the vasalized
kings did not convert to the foreign
religions. And because the conversion
did not happen at the top, there was no
top tobottom push, top to down push
using the full might of the state
apparatus, military, bureaucracy,
everything to convert and that's why
Indians did not convert. Thanks to our
kings and queens, even those who had
become vasalized, even they did not give
up. Is that the case today? Ask
yourselves,
is that the case today? Today you don't
have kings, you have politicians, and
what are they doing? some of them
hypothetically.
So now today our culture is in under
real threat. It's under siege.
Yajj Navalia says, "Why did the
monotheisms that form a majority of the
world today emerge out of tiny regions
of West Asia and only in the last 2,000
3,000 years in the 10,000 in the 100,000
plus years of existence of homo sapiens
in such a relatively w large world? How
is it the case that monotheism never
developed independently in any other
region of the world except the Israel
Palestine region?"
Interesting question, right?
See monotheistic religions if you see
they tend to develop in desert regions.
Wherever you have lush forests and and
abundance
and the and the land gives you plenty of
resources. You will find that people
will have polytheistic beliefs because
life is not hard and everything is
beautiful. Everything is divine. So you
will see divinity in trees. You will see
divinity in in in in
mountains, in hills. You will see
divinity in animals. You will see
divinity in each other. And that's why
wherever you have a land of plenty and
abundance, you will have polytheistic
religions that develop from in these
regions. But where you have a land of
scarcity, a desert region, where you
have to fight for every morsel to eat,
you to fight and kill just to put food
on the table. That's a region, that's a
land of scarcity.
And somehow it's in these places that
monotheistic religions develop.
I mean even if you look at Mongolia
you could say it's a really harsh land
very harsh climate and there are times
in winter where you know food is not
abundant at all. You have to fight for
that and yet there are Mongolia is full
of forests. It has the step of course
but it also has rivers and lakes and
forests. So Mongolia also developed a
polytheistic religion. What today is
called Tangriism based on the name of
one god but it's a polytheistic
religion. So wherever you have a land of
scarcity
that's where a monotheistic religion
develops somehow because there is no
divinity anywhere. So you have to invent
some god one god
possibly possibly that's the case. Hm.
So uh
so that's why monotheism came out of
this region. The Israel Palestine, the
Israel region, the deserts of Arabia,
that region. I mean you could claim that
even Egypt is mostly desert but Egyptian
civilization flourished on the banks of
the Nile which is a region of plenty and
that's why they had a monothe
polytheistic culture. So polytheism
emerges from lands of plenty. Monotheism
comes from desert regions.
Interesting question by feminist slayer.
Can you explain the historical
significance of sitting bull especially
his leadership in the battle of little
little big horn and his role in
resisting US government policies against
native Americans. Okay, we'll go into
who sitting bull was and what his
significance was. But all of this what
we're going to discuss it is in the
context of the of the
of the war against the native Americans
the American Indian wars it's called I
think American Indian wars I think it is
called it was see
the Europeans
it's the French the Spanish the French
and the British they came from Europe
they discovered this land they knew this
land existed because of you know
Columbus and all
And then they started colonizing the
land. You know the Nazis, you know Nazis
are very, you know, Nazis are evil. Do
we all agree Nazi Germany was evil?
What was the deal with Nazi Germany?
What was one of the objectives of Nazi
Germany? One of the objectives of Nazi
Germany was to conquer more land for
German people. Lebanon's realm, a large
region of land where only Germans can be
settled so that Germans will have more
land to live in. That was one of the
objectives of the Nazi government,
right? To find more land, if necessary,
clear that land of the original people
and settle Germans there. Very evil,
right? Very, very evil. Nazi
Nazi level evil.
Now what were the
Spanish, French and English doing in
America when they started conquering and
colonizing? They were doing exactly
that.
They wanted this huge land for
themselves. So what do you do? You
exterminate the natives. You genocide
the natives. You do this on a scale
Nazis could not even have imagined.
That's what happened. And the American
Indian Wars are that the genocide of the
natives.
That's what these nations in the
Americas are. Settler colonial nations
that are that have been built on stolen
land as a consequence of genocide and
slavery
and genocide on a scale that Nazi
Germany could not imagine.
So once the Anglo started settling in in
the eastern part of North America, they
started expanding westwards. The great
western frontier and where wherever they
went, they they encountered native
people.
So what do you do? You want the land. So
you defeat them militarily. If they
fight, you fight back. And once you
subjugate them, you massacre as many as
possible. Whoever is left, you sign a
treaty. So it becomes legal. You sign a
treaty that relegates the survivors to a
reservation.
A reservation which is like a
concentration camp essentially. It's
land where there's nothing available.
You find the most barren land and settle
people there. Settle the natives there.
And the rest of the land becomes yours.
So you did a fair treaty. See, we signed
a treaty. You see, it's legal. We did
not do this by force. We had a treaty.
And they did this over and over again
with various tribes that they they they
they subjugated.
And from the 1700s all the way to the
beginning of the 1900s, the Americans
did that, the Anglo from the 1600s,
1700s all the way to the until the end
of the 19th century. This went on the
American Indian Wars.
Okay. It was the systematic genocide
and of the native American American
people, the theft of their land and the
relegation of their of the survivors
to essentially concentration camps,
small parcels of land which would be
given which would where there's nothing
really of use and you settle them there
and that's where natives still live
today whoever has survived. Right?
That's the deal.
So now now that you understand what
happened, what was done and how this
nation of the United States was created
right now let's talk about sitting bull
sitting bull was the chief was one of
the chiefs of the Lacakota tribe it's a
plains tribe plains Indians they were
called now what the plains the great
plains the the flat plains of the
Americas so let me give you uh let's
let's let's put that on the screen so
that you understand the geographical
extent of the of the lands of the plains
Indians. Okay. Uh plains
Indians Indians. Uh what was the
territory like
territory? Let's go to images. Hopefully
there's a map somewhere.
And we're talking about not just Yeah,
now we're talking. Look at this here.
It's actually even bigger than that. The
actual extent was bigger than that.
They're just showing some part of it. It
it encompasses the United States and
Canada and it goes all the way north. It
goes all the way north to further north
than the further north than what is
being shown here. Let me see. Do I have
I think all of this history is nicely
suppressed. Nicely suppressed.
Anyway, they had a vast territory.
Even if you look at just the US, it's
it's a massive territory in the United
States. Uh and it was more than what's
being shown over here. So that was the
dominion the domain of the plains
Indians and they were slowly
systematically you know deprived of
their of their land. Now let's once
again go back and let's see sitting bull
sitting.
So he was a leader of the lot. That's
what he looked like. This is an
artificially colorized photograph of
him. Uh this is his face. That's what he
looked like. And he spent his entire
life fighting the invaders.
his entire life fighting the invaders.
That's what he did. And uh so in the
1870s somewhere he fought against the
American invaders, the the Anglo
invaders. And there was this very famous
battle called the battle of Little
Bigghorn in which there was this this
this individual called George Kuster.
George Kuster. Let's Google that guy. He
was the leader of the invas invasive
band. George Kuster, Lieutenant Colonel
was he whatever George Kuster
and he launched an invasion of Lakota
land and the battle happened battle of
little little big horn in which the
Americans the Anglos suffered a
catastrophic defeat. So this was Kuster
who who maybe was over ambitious or
maybe he was overconfident and he and
his forces were were wiped out in the
battle of the little big horn. But
eventually the Americans won and the
Lakota were also deprived of their land
and uh sitting bull was sent into exile
in Canada or wherever and he spent his
entire life the rest of his life also in
some way or the other opposing the
invaders and occupiers of his land. So
that's the leader the historical
significance of setting bull. There were
so many um you know resistance fighters
from the native Americans who all met
you know not a nice end at the hands of
the Americans and sitting bull I think
he died at an older age in exile in
Canada away from his land away from his
people and that's the deal so the story
of the native Americans is a horrific
tragic story a story of genocide and and
a story of u their land being stolen
being stolen to create an artificial
nation.
Okay? And this was done along the same
lines of what the Nazis wanted to do in
Europe, but on a scale that the Nazis
could not imagine that vast a
continent-sized scale.
Anonymous scientist says according to
Herodotus Neco II an Egyptian ruler sent
Phoenician mariners to find a sea route
around Africa then known as Libya and
the Phoenicians succeeded in finding a
sea route through the cape of Cape of
Good Hope to India
or maybe not to India. He's not
mentioning India here. So why do we give
credit to the Portuguese there then?
Well, you see the Phoenicians were not
Christians. They were not white
Europeans and neither was Neco II. These
were brownskinned people. They were not
Christian and that's why they must not
get any credit. See that's how the world
works today. All credit is given to
Europeans and Christians especially what
happened in the past 500 years.
Everything all the credit has to be
given to Europeans. If the Europeans
discovered arithmetic, the decimal
system through the Arabs which came from
the Indians, the best they will do is
give a little bit of credit to the Arabs
and then just digest all of that and say
that we discovered everything. So that's
that's what the Europeans have been
doing the past 500 years. So look, Vasco
the Gama discovered something, but it
was it was known for a very very long
time all of that. Just because a white
Christian guy discovered it doesn't mean
that he was the first person to discover
something. People lived at the Cape of
Good Hope. They knew that something
existed on the other other side on both
sides. Right? In in in Eastern Africa,
you had Indians who lived all over the
place. So this is the euro this is the
consequence of the euroentric world that
we live in today. The accidental centric
western world that we live in today
where all the credit has to be given to
Europeans and white people.
Right. Next.
Somi says, "How did the Vikings suddenly
rise in the sixth in in the 9th century
despite being isolated and insignificant
prior to the Viking age?"
Okay, let's go to the map to understand
uh what are we talking about here. Yes,
you are right. The Viking age certainly
begins around the 8th 9th century. What
happened suddenly? How did they become
so significant? Let's go to the map.
We'll go to the Viking area. So, we're
talking about Western Europe here
and we have this this bunch of islands
called today the United Kingdom which
was the British islands, the English
islands and to the northeast of that you
have the Scandinavian region which is
Denmark, Norway and Sweden. Okay, you
have Sweden here, you have Norway here
and you have Denmark here. The Vikings
were mostly Danes and Norwegians. the
Scandinavian people, they were called
Vikings. So you can see that between
Scandinavia and the British islands, you
have the North Sea. And it's pretty it's
pretty vast actually. If you look at the
distance, it's not small. It's not
insignificant. It's about more than 500
km of open sea and pretty rough sea and
very cold sea. So back in the day,
people just had boats, right? People
just had boats.
So how do you so you could not so people
who lived in Scandinavia Scandinavia
would not even know that 550 60
kilometers away this this bunch of
islands or if they knew then it would be
some some faraway mythical place if the
existence of England was known so that's
how it was the distances were very
immense and the technology did not exist
then how did the Viking age erupt out of
nowhere as always
technological ical advance.
The Vikings developed long boats.
Long boats were essentially small ships
that could be crewed by 10 20 people who
would have sails as well as oes and they
were pretty hardy. They could survive
the rough seas. And secondly, the
Vikings discovered some sunstone or
something. So, so in this part of the
world, northern Europe, the atla, the
the the eastern Atlantic region, the
North Sea region, the the climate is
terrible in the sense that it's always
cloudy. It's always overcast. It's
raining all the time. So, you hardly see
the sun, the the sun. And if you don't
see the sun, then how will you navigate
properly? So, the Vikings discovered
some stone, some translucent stone that
if you put put against the sky, even if
it's overcast, you can kind of detect
where the sun is.
And using that stone and using the long
long ships, the Ving Viking long ships,
they were able to start reaching
England. And that's where the Viking age
begins. And where does the Viking age
begin? It begins. Let's find the place
again. Okay. So, we are looking, let's
zoom out. We're talking about the United
Kingdom. Now, let's slowly zoom in. Here
you have the city of London, right?
We're going to go north. London,
Cambridge, Manchester. We go further
north. We don't go all the way to
Edinburgh, but we kind of come here.
This place is called Lindisfarn. It's
also called Holy Island. And this is the
first place where a Viking landing
happened as far as I as I know. May have
happened elsewhere, but this is the
first properly recorded incident. So the
Vikings came here and they sacked the
Lindesfarn Abbey and they stole all the
gold and valuables
and then they discovered yeah we can
reach England we can sack these weak
people these these people and uh steal
their land and and valuables and there's
a lot of uh good valuable land there
where where we can do farming and so on.
So the word spread among the Vikings
among the Scandinavians and they started
organizing these raiding parties and
eventually the raiding parties parties
became very significant and this they
started conquering England and that's
how the Viking age began. It all began
with technological advances.
All empires that conquer they conquer
because of technological advances and
technological advantages they develop
over
the people they conquer.
Sam says, "We're going to talk about the
Cuban missile crisis. Please explain the
Cuban missile crisis of 1962." Samar
prammanic.
Okay. So, we're talking about the cold
war. The the second world war ended in
1945 and then the world was very rapidly
divided into two camps. The US-led camp
with its vasals and the USSR le camp
with its vasals.
And the Americans uh they were the
people they were the country that first
developed the the atomic bomb. And by
the 1960s they had about I don't know 20
25,000 nuclear warheads including 3,000
plus deployed in Europe against the
USSR.
Imagine more than roughly 25,000
nuclear warheads the Americans had. And
more than 3,000 of these were deployed
in Europe aimed at the USSR.
And at that time the Soviets had also
you know developed atomic uh weapons.
And the Soviets had maybe 3 4,000
nuclear warheads only a fraction of what
the Americans had. And they feared that
you know because of the American nuclear
warheads and missiles on European soil
very close to our borders pointed at us.
It's a huge problem. We have to do
something about this. So the Soviets
sent dispatched a shipment or maybe
multiple shipments of shipments of
nuclear tipped missiles to Cuba. Where
is Cuba in case some of you don't know?
Let's go to Cuba. All right. So let's
cross the Atlantic and we are talking
about Hispanola.
I'm sorry this not Hispanola. This is
Hispanola. Hispanola. This is Cuba. Cuba
is in the Caribbean region just south of
Florida. You know the distance between
Florida and and Cuba is what two 230 or
so kilometers. So this is Cuba and Cuba
used to be a US Vasal but then there was
a revolution in Cuba and Fidel Castro
came to power and Fidel Fidel Castro was
a leftist and he aligned himself with
the USSR. So the USSR sent nuclear
tipped missiles to Cuba and these were
then deployed in Cuba aimed at the US.
Obviously, if the US can position
nuclear weapons in Europe aimed at the
USSR, why can't the USSR pay them back
in kind by deploying missiles in Cuba?
So, the Americans had these U2 spy plane
program. They had this extremely high
altitude spy spy aircraft called U2
aircraft. uh they would fly above the
range of any known missile at the time
and they would have these overflights
over Russia or China also over Cuba and
and they would take photographs of what
was happening on the ground and during
these warfights they discovered that
there are missiles probably Soviet
missiles in Cuba and that's where the
alarm bells start ringing and eventually
Kennedy addresses his nation and says
that there is this threat to the US the
Soviets have deployed Cub nuclear
missiles aimed at us on Cuba and uh this
led to a period of extremely tense
diplomacy and uh a confrontation between
between the navies and air forces of the
two nations. There was an incident where
a Soviet submarine in the Gulf of Mexico
it uh it was patrolling there and the
American warships detected it and
started dropping depth charges at it at
this submarine. A depth depth charge is
a bomb that is designed to detonate at a
certain depth below the surface of the
sea. So you can set it to detonate at 50
m below the sea surface maybe 70 m 100 m
200 300 whatever you can set the
detonation depth of this bomb. So these
are called depth charges. So the Soviet
submarine was there, diesel submarine I
believe, not nuclear submarine, diesel
submarine. And the Americans started,
American warship started detonating
depth charges to drive this submarine to
the surface. The submarine surfaced and
then there was an American helicopter
hoing over it at a height of about 10 15
m and they started firing rounds at the
submarine,
firing machine gun rounds at the
submarine. Now the the the protocol was
that you don't do live firing on the
opponent unless there's a war. So the
captain of the submarine
thought that World War II has broken out
and he had a nuclear tipped torpedo
and he wanted to use it
but there was a political officer. So
generally what happens in a submarine
and what used to happen was that the the
the the submarine's captain and his
second in command had to agree both of
them had to agree if both agreed they
could launch a nuclear weapon but on
this particular submarine there was a
highranking Soviet political officer
also who was there and that person
disagreed that's why it did not happen
so the world came to the brink of
nuclear war eventually a diplomatic
consens diplomatic uh settlement was was
reached. The the Soviets agreed to
withdraw to to withdraw the nuclear
missiles from Cuba and the Americans
secretly agreed to withdraw American
nuclear missiles from Turkey that were
aimed at the USSR. Today you have
American nuclear missiles in Turkey,
aimed at Russia. So that's kind of what
this what this Cuban missile crisis was.
The US president was John F. Kennedy at
the time. It was 62, not 63.
So yeah, that's what it was in brief. It
it is probably the closest the world
came to a nuclear exchange. So the
Soviets had about 3,000 plus nuclear
warheads. The Americans had 25,000
roughly nuclear warheads. And that would
have been a catastrophe if a nuclear
exchange had happened.
Adwit
Ashwani says, "What horrors did Belgium
do in our DRC?" the democrat the
democratic republic of Congo.
So today's Congo region what what
happened there? Once again we go to the
map. So first of all we understand what
this place is. It's in Africa. We go to
Africa. Where is the DRC? Look at this
place over here. DRC. So this is the
Congo region and the Belgians occupied
this region from about 18 from the 1880s
until the until the 1910s 1920s.
Belgium's king Leopold essentially owned
this land. Okay. And they extracted the
land of land land of everything of any
value that existed here. Mainly rubber
plantations. Okay. So now we understand
we'll close the map.
So Congo is rich in forests. So the
Belgians planted rubber trees
everywhere, rubber plantations and they
enslaved the locals. The locals all
became the property of the king. the
local people who lived there became the
property of the king and they would then
have to do whatever they were told by
their Belgian overlords. So there was a
major Belgian military presence there
and a major Belgian missionary presence
there. So the people were enslaved. They
were all put to work on the rubber
plantations and various mines or
whatever for what whatever other mineral
wealth etc. Congo head. So so rubber
plantations, mines, all of that. That's
where the people were made to work
forcibly.
Children were made to work.
Child labor, slave labor, doesn't
matter. It's good as long as the the
Belgian king, you know, profits.
So the Belgians were enslaved. Sorry,
the the the Congolese, the people of
Congo were enslaved. Now what happened?
They were brutalized. They were many of
them were overworked. Some of them many
of them were worked to death. And
everybody every every slave was given a
daily kota that you need to bring this
amount of of produce or or material to
the to the to your white boss every day.
And if if there was a shortfall of even
a little bit then they would meet brutal
punishments.
One of the common punishments was to
chop off the person's hand and sometimes
they would not chop the guy's hands off,
they would chop the hands of his kids,
right? And this was widespread
brutal treatment. So today in the 20th
century at least in Belgium there was
this famous chocolate that you could
buy. What was the chocolate? It was
hands. Cut hands.
Would you like to see is true? I'm I'm
not making it up. Okay. Let's let's
let's see.
So one is that another is a tetany which
we'll talk about. Okay. Belgian
chocolateate
hence
chocolate unwrap hence whatever they
call look at this look at this
I think it's still available
this is
you know essentially all those hands of
the Africans they chopped off look at
this now look at this this blatant
racism still continues look here can you
see children with their hands chopped
This is what Belgium did. This is just
one example of what Belgium did. See
these are children. Children with their
arms, with their hands chopped off,
legs, hands as well as feet chopped off.
And they celebrated this through these
chocolates. They still do
now. I think it's called anter chocolate
hands or whatever.
But this is how they celebrated this.
There is another there is another very
famous uh chocolate confectionary that
is that was available
in Europe in the 20th century. It was
called tetra
tetra bomb.
Look at this
heads.
Heads. Now it's called tetto shula. And
this is it's very tasty. And now it is
not shaped like the head of a person,
but it still has this vaguely head-like
shape.
As a child living in Europe in the
1980s, I also ate some of these
chocolates without knowing what it was
at the time. It was very tasty.
Yeah. So what was the brutality that was
done to the Africans?
They were enslaved. They were worked to
death. There were brutal punishments.
Hands chopped off, feet chopped off,
children with arms and limbs amputated,
people killed, people executed for
showing the slightest disobedience.
Um, children and families kidnapped and
placed in internment or or concentration
camps. Sexual abuse, widespread sexual
abuse by the Belgians. brutal horrific
abuse by the Belgians and the
destruction of the local culture and the
imposition of Christianity in a
systematic manner. All of this was done
by Belgian Belgium between the 1880s and
the 1910s or 1920s.
Yeah, good fun, wasn't it?
For the Belgians, not for the not for
the natives.
Okay. Okay. No says in premodern times
did China and Europe have thousands of
indoamas jatis not to be confused with
varnas but jatis as we had in India. So
even today people are kind of vaguely
aware of jati but we had this extremely
intricate super complicated system of
tens of thousands of jatis in India
small clan-like communities where people
would marry within the community with a
set of rules and you would not marry
outside that sort of thing it it emerged
maybe during the Gupta empire period or
something like that perhaps
u so we had these thousands of
indogamous jatis in India did the
Chinese have Did the Europeans have it?
The Chinese had a four layered cast
system.
What I mean what what is this guy
saying? Pagaloya.
What is he saying? Let me show you
something, my friends. China.
Google it yourself if you want to. China
for occupations, not occupation.
Occupations. Let's ask Wikipedia what it
has to say. Okay.
four categories of the people
an occupation classification used in
China ancient China by confusion or
legally scholars as far as the late shoe
dynasty and part of the social structure
and so on so on so on from 10,000 from
146 to 256 BC so what was the division
the shei or the warrior nobles later on
gentry scholars the nong is the peasant
farmers the gong is the artisans and
craftsmen and the shang the merchants
and traders. So you had four classes or
casts of society in traditional Chinese
society.
So you you would not really have they
did not have really this system of
jatis. They had this four tired cast
system or class system in China. And
people would marry typically you marry
among your social equals right? That's
what society has always shown. Whenever
you have a highly organized society
which is typical of all civilizations
advanced civilizations you have a highly
organized and stratified society every
civilization has this feature so
generally people will marry people who
are their social equals they won't marry
down you won't marry up generally so so
you that's what you would have in China
of course there would be some some
people who would be have practiced a
certain skill or a certain trade for for
god know centuries various generations
they would probably want to there would
have been some cases where you had some
sort of endogamy but in China generally
you had this four classes or four casts
and people would marry within the the
cast that that was the situation in
Europe what was the situation Europe was
a feudal society so you had the king at
the top then you had the the aristocracy
or nobility which is the the king and
his vasals
the people with the with the with the
means to do violence
Then you had the clergy, the the church
people and then you had the peasants.
Eventually a new class emerged which is
the the merchants. So you had three,
four, five different classes in Europe
also and people would only marry within
their own class. But they also did not
have this jati system.
They they had I mean if you look at
English surnames Smith, Fletcher,
Thatcher, Hatcher, whatever these are
all occupation based surnames
but they did not they they would
probably marry among their own class. So
they did not have the Jati system the
way you had in India for about 1500
years. So yeah, China was different,
Europe was different, Japan also had its
own system. Okay, we'll not go there
today. But yeah, it was different from
the Indian jati system which was very
very complex. Thousands maybe tens of
thousands of jatis.
Okay. Amisha says what was religion like
in ancient Persia before Zoroastrianism.
Very simple answer. Vic religion. That
was it. Okay. Don't believe me? Right?
Let's see what what twisted version of
my answer Wikipedia will give you or or
Google will give you. Okay. Uh so let's
go to Google. Okay. What was the
religion of Persia before? Let's ask
them. What was the religion of Persia
before Zoro? Yeah, there you have it.
Zorosism. Let's see what Google AI says.
Before Zoroastrinism, the Persians
followed the ancient Indo-Iranian
religion, a shared ancestor of both the
Vic religion and the religion of the
early Iranian. What what utter nonsense
this polytheistic tradition worshiped
multi.
When I say utter nonsense, it means that
it's an ancestor of the Vic religion.
What absolute nonsense. The Vic religion
was the ancestral religion of all of
these things. So this polytheistic
tradition worshiped multiple deities
with aurora mista. How can aurora mazda
exist before zurastinism? What? See this
is complete contradic contradictory
nonsense and mitra being prominent
figures. Worship of fire and blah blah
soma
worship of other gods. Um this ancient
faith was a common ancestor of the Vic
religion of India and the ancient
beliefs of the Iranian peoples. What
evidence do you have to support this?
Nothing absolute nothing lies
shared with Vic religion. See they don't
want to say it was the Vic religion. But
the truth is that even through these
distortions you can see it was the Vic
religion. And if you go to Wikipedia it
will have a different version of the
same nonsense. What evidence do they
have that there was an ancestor of the
Vic religion anywhere? Show me evidence.
not someone's claim or a consensus
consensus of of of of professors. I
don't want a consensus. I want evidence,
hard undeniable evidence, not someone's
opinion. Oh, so and so imminent
professor said that and seven other
imminent professors agreed. I don't care
about anyone's opinions, no matter how
imminent they may be in someone's
opinion. Again, opinion, I want hard
evidence.
What was the religion of Persia before
Zorastrianism?
If there was a religion, was it the
ancestor of Vic Hinduism or was it Vic
Hinduism itself? So then the question is
what was the ancestor of Vic Hinduism?
Do we have an answer? There was nothing.
It was just Vic Hinduism and the
pre-vedic Hinduism. But it was all it
would be categorized as Hinduism only if
you want to use the term Hinduism like
we do today. So the ancient religion in
Persia before Zaratustra emerged was the
old Indo Iranian Vic religion.
Okay, long question here by UMAX. In May
2025, a paper was published in Nature
showing that ancient DNA revealed 3,000
years of genetic continuity in the
northern Iranian plateau from the copper
age to the Societ Empire with no
evidence of step migration into Iran. No
Aran invasion. Oh my god. According to
the step theory,
it was earlier invasions now is
migrations. Migrations into Iran
according to the step theory from
Central Asia should have occurred about
1,000 BC or 1500 BC. Yeah. same RN
invasion simultaneously in India and
Persia that's the claim however the
study found no such gene flow sadly
tragically this is significant because
the step theory claims that both
Indo-Arians and Iranians migrated from
central Asia between 1200 BC to 1,000 BC
or 1500 BC to 1,000 BC whatever yet the
new findings so show no synashta or step
ancestry in the iron age samples which
presents a major challenge to the step
theory I hope you've read the paper
while it does not directly address the
debate the genetic results clearly
indicate the absence of step ad mixture
in iron age.
No matter how you try to spin this
theory,
Arian invasion theory or Arian migration
theory or or or tourism theory or
whatever picnic theory no matter what
distorted twisted interpretation you
create that that people came from the
step well eventually the truth will come
out. I haven't read this paper but you
clearly have summarized it properly. I
will look into it.
So clearly this is another blow to this
Iranian invasion migration claim.
And the the crux of the matter of this
of this Ian invasion claim or or
migration claim is that Sanskrit and
Hinduism came to India and Persia from
outside of India from from central Asia.
Prove it. Prove it. What proof do you
have beyond someone's opinion? Nothing.
So this yeah and and because there is no
proof of this that's why they have
brought the genetic angle in that maybe
there was some gene flow which indicates
there was perhaps language and and and
religion flow if you have a gigantic
region like India Persia put together
and it's so prosperous mainly India then
obviously people from all over the rest
of the rest of the world will want to
migrate there so you will have some some
small trickles of of step ad mixture
coming in does it mean that they brought
the language and culture and everything?
Such utter illogical nonsense. And yet
so many people believe it because that's
what you are taught in your textbooks in
school and that's what your professors
believe because they are because they
they don't don't want to learn anything
new anymore. So this theory
is still the favorite theory of the
white man and the favorite theory of the
colonized Indian. But it will die a slow
death this theory because no evidence is
ever going to emerge which will prove
any of the central claims of this
theory.
Okay. Amisha has two questions. Firstly,
what's the difference between Persians
and the Arabs? Secondly, what are the
similarities and differences between the
Persians, the Ottomans, Turks and the
Arabs? So essentially what Amisha is
asking is what's the difference between
the Persians, the Turks and the Arabs?
So first first of all if you call a
Persian person
Arabic you're Arabs they'll be offended.
Okay. Um if you call a Persian person
that you're Turkish they'll not like it
either and so on because they're Persian
right? If you call if you call an Indian
something else the Indians will be
offended. Sim similar similar thing. So
what's the difference? The Persians are
an Indo-Iranian people.
The true Persians
were just like people from western
India. Today if you look at Persians and
some of them look like white people
because they were under Turk occupation
for many centuries and the Turks brought
in people from the Caucasus region and
settled them in in Iran present day Iran
and that's how and because everybody had
the same religion they started inter
intermingling intermaring and that's how
many Persians became kind of
Europeanized. So today you'll see many
Persians with blue eyes or green eyes.
Many some of them will have blonde hair.
But the original parhua people, the
original Persian people look like this.
Okay. Um so the Persians, the true
Persians are our close cousins. They're
our brothers and sisters essentially. If
you are a Indian from the north and west
of India, the original Persians were
just like us, same ethnicity.
Today's Persians are maybe somewhat
different. They may have kind of get got
mixed up with these outside
the immigrants who were brought in from
outside but culturally they are still
Persian at least the language. See the
Persian language is very close to Indian
languages. It has nothing in similar
with the Arabic languages with the
Arabic language. Of course a lot of
Arabic loan words are used in Persian
language today. Just like in Hindi we
use a lot of Arabic and Turk and Persian
loan words because of the history right
of foreign occupation of India. So the
Persians are an Indo-Iranian people.
They are not a Semitic people like the
Arabs. Okay different different
ethnicity. The Turks are neither Persian
nor Semitic. They're Turic. Their origin
was in Central Asia. Their deep origin
is in the Mongolia region where the
horns emerged and the horns were the
were the ancestors of the Turk Turk
people and the Turkish people were the
ancestors of today's Turks. But if you
look at the genetics of today's Turkish
people in Turkey, they are like more
than 90 95% Greek and that's a whole
different story. So that's the
similarities, differences and so on.
What's the similarities between the
Turks, Arabs and Persians? Religion,
Islam. The Persians today are are Shia
Isl Shia Shia Muslims and most Arabs and
Turks are Sunni Muslims.
Yeah. So that's the differences and
similarities between these three ethnic
groups.
Okay. Maji restoration. Amisha says how
did the Maji dynasty restoration change
Japan's political and economical
landscape? And Nirvana Shanks says the
Maji restoration crushed Buddhism and
old traditions. What happened? How did
it change society?
So what is this major restoration? Did
it really crush Buddhism and old
traditions?
The major restoration was a coup in
Japan. It was essentially a takeover of
power from the emperor by by a bunch of
bureaucrats by a bunch of officials. But
they did not kill the emperor or depos.
They turned the emperor into a
figurehead, into a puppet.
They forced him to eat beef.
The emperor was a teenager.
with very little power. So the
bureaucrats turned him into a puppet and
they unleashed what is now called the
Maji restoration which is named after
the Maji emperor even though he was
merely a puppet in the hands of these uh
officials court officials.
So, Japan
has a 2,000 roughly 2,000 year history
of a syncratic culture.
Shinto and Indian culture mixed
together. The Indian culture is mainly
manifested in the form of Buddhism. But
you will see every Indian god being
woripped in Japan with with Japanese
names. Saraswati is Benzin. Um Ganesha
is Kangitan. You have Kuber. You have
Lord Shiva. You have Bra. to have every
Indian god worshiped in Japan uh through
various local names and all of this is
is portrayed as being part of Buddhism
in Japan.
So for at least 15,600 years close to
2,000 years, Japan practiced a syncratic
form of Shinto which is the native
culture and Buddhism, Hinduism which is
which came through China from India and
which also mixed synchronized
beautifully with the local culture
because both are polytheistic systems
and both are super compatible with each
other.
Now and and the samurai class of Japan
was Buddhist class. They abhor beef.
They would never eat beef for a thousand
years. No Japanese ate beef. Beef was
taboo just like in India. And the
samuras were mainly vegetarians. They
ate some fish. And they were the you
could say the cratrias or the rajuts of
of Japan. Not the rajmuts, the chhatrias
of Japan. They were the warrior class.
And they held the real power in Japan.
So the major restoration was about
destroying the system of the samuris
first of all that's the that was the
first objective and what did the the
maji restoration did the officials who
were who really had the had the real
power they brought in Americans
to train the troops in western warfare
methodologies they brought in gunpowder
and guns and machine guns you know those
gatling you know those primitive gatling
guns and all that and they started
employing a whole different set
tactics and strategies compared to the
samurai who were steeped in ancient
tradition and then they wiped out the
samurai. So the entire power structure
of Japan was was made to disappear and
all the power then became concentrated
in the name of the emperor. But the
actual power was with the it lay with
the court officials.
That's first. But the samurai were
Buddhists. So you had to attack Buddhism
also, right? Otherwise the people will
still there'll be social issues. So then
they tried to portray Buddhism as a
foreign religion. And they tried to
destroy Buddhism. Did not work. Did not
work. Buddhism they could not approve
from Japan. did not work. But what what
did happen is that because of their
efforts to destroy Buddhism, today
Buddhism is looked upon in Japan as a
foreign religion, a religion that came
from outside. It's a Japanese religion.
It's it's practiced by lots of people,
but it's a religion that people in Japan
today see as something that came from
outside, came from India.
Before the Maji restoration, it was seen
as a purely Japanese religion. So that's
what it did. So the old way of life was
destroyed. The samurai tradition was
destroyed. Buddhism was now regarded
differently. Uh all power was
concentrated in the in the figure head
of the emperor but it was actually
wielded by his officials and uh that
laid led gave rise to the Japanese
imperial era which ended with two
American atomic tests on the people of
Japan.
Okay Swami this is the last question.
Swami says who are the Hugenots? Why did
the Hugenats fail to make France
Protestant? Also, why did the Spanish
Armada fail to make England Catholic
again? Second question first, why did
the Spanish Armada fail to make England
Catholic again? Because the Armada was
defeated.
That's why they failed to make England
Catholic again. As simple as that, they
were defeated. The Spanish Armada was
this huge fleet of I don't know 3
million ships the Spanish had sent to
conquer England. They were so confident
they sent all kinds of extra stuff with
the ships. Several hundred trips but the
English were able to defeat the Spanish
Armada which was a catastrophe for Spain
and the Spaniards wanted to turn England
Catholic again. England was by that time
a Protestant kingdom because of the
great exploits of Shri Henry VIII.
Uh we'll not go into that story right
now. So that's why the Spanish Armada
could not make England Catholic again
because it failed. It was routed. Who
were the Hugenauts? The Hugenauts were
Calvinists, Protestants.
Who was Calvin? John Calvin. If you go
to Geneva, the University of Geneva,
you'll see a mural with a with a set of
human figures on it. One of which is
Calvin. Uh, now Calvin was a was a
reformer. He was a Protestant. He wanted
to reform Christianity from the religion
of the popes which he said which he said
was very very very
uh which was which was corrupted
probably according to him. So we he
needed to bring Christianity back to its
roots which is the austere
fundamentalist root roots of
Christianity. So that and the people who
followed him became known as the
protestants or Calvinists. So the hug
hugenauts were Calvinists and
Protestants same thing essentially and
they were French and some prominent
people became hugenauts and that's why
they gained some prominence in society
and some small regions in France kind of
became protest and very small it was a
very minor thing but overall France was
Catholic a deeply Catholic country and
they didn't like this so that's why
there was this social strife and there
was there was some a few massacres there
was this religious wars in France
and this was all in the 16th century and
eventually many of the Hugenauts they
crossed the Atlantic Ocean and landed in
uh the new world and they tried to
establish a foothold there. Some of it
succeeded, some of it most of it failed
and uh yeah that's the Hugats. So they
failed to make France Protestant because
France was overwhelmingly Catholic. All
the authorities were Catholic. The
kings, the kings were Catholic and so on
and they did not want this new nonsense
to come in and to upend society and
that's why this was crushed.
Okay, end of the questions for today.
Let me take some questions from the live
chat. A few
um
Okay, in case you have some Okay, Shiv
says, "Eat lamb's eggs and lamb. Stop
the lentils overdose." All right.
Okay, you're discussing something else
entirely over here. A
uh Japanese PM Ishiba resigned. Well,
Japan is a revolving door prime
ministership.
Japan is not a sovereign country. Please
understand that
Japan is not a sovereign country. Their
prime ministers don't matter. Only one
prime minister has mattered in Japan's
history after 1945 and he was
assassinated. It doesn't matter.
PMs come and PM go. PMs go. they don't
really are able to achieve anything.
Uh
do we have super chats? Oh, we have
super chats. Please don't take any more
super chats please. I'm ending the
stream now. But let me take these three
since since these people have taken
super chats. Gpati says you say Japan
has been a vasal of the US since the
second world war. But I disagree. Japan
has been a vasal since 1853 since Perry
forced them to open. The process started
at that time.
The process started at the time. But
Japan was not a vasad at that time
because you do not have a US written
Japanese constitution and you do not
have a US occupation of Japan. Japan
went against the US. Japan fought the
US. Japan defeated the the so the
Russians. Japan invaded much of Asia. Do
you does it look like the actions of a
vasal? Completely independent actions.
Do you understand that forcing somebody
to to end the isolation strategy,
isolation policy of several decades
doesn't make that nation a vasal? It
simply opens up the nation and then the
nation realized that if we don't become
like the westerners, we'll be enslaved
by them. And that's why Japan underwent
the major restoration and that's how
Japan became this this hegemonic
expansionist imperial power which is the
exact opposite of a vasal. So please
understand this, understand the
difference. There are nuances that you
have to understand. You have to take
your analysis deeper than surface level.
Secret billionaire says according to
Bhagat Gita, vera isn't based on birth
and family but nowadays we don't follow
it. Question one, according to what is
truth according to Hindism? I am I don't
know. Question two, when did the switch
happen? Who could have done it? Look, I
I don't know about this entire thing.
Look
you you are so the question you're
asking it's it's the presupposition
you're making is that the Bhagat Gita is
the one book we should refer to.
Is that the only holy book in our our
culture and civilization? We have
hundreds thousands of holy books. We
have a whole library that's holy. A
massive library that's holy.
We have the Vedas. The Vedas don't refer
to any verna. Sure. Right. But
eventually society changes.
Our society has evolved over thousands
of years. The Bhagat Gita, Bhagat Gita
was spoken by Shri Krishna on the
battlefield to Arjun. That happened
maybe four, five, 6 th 6,000 years ago.
But that was a modern period compared to
the Vic age which happened several
thousand years before that. So during
the Vic age society was different. There
was no varnati.
During the Mahabharat era once again we
do not have varnati as far as we know.
Or if we had it, it was not based on
birth of family. But during the Gupta
era, which is the past 1500 years, this
is 1500 years ago. Society was
different. Our society is so so ancient.
We've had time periods of thousands of
years where lots of changes happened. At
some point in time, something other that
happened and indogami came in and
certain changes happened in society.
So I am it looks like this system of of
of
jati that people become the society
becomes indoggamous within the jati
system it probably happened about 1500
or so years before today during the
gupta era probably what is the truth
according to Hinduism there are so many
truths according to Hinduism see if we
have this abraic monotheistic outlook in
which there is only one truth
then it's no longer a hindu Hindu way of
looking at things,
right? So that's what I would say. The
the truth is complicated. There's not
one truth. We are a society that's been
around for 10,000 plus years. We have
had different truths in different
thousand year periods. Understand that.
That's the deal.
Okay. Last question for today. Spur
says, "Is the Mecca site in Caba related
to ancient Hinduism and has connections
to Shiva?" I am not aware of any of such
thing because I've not looked into the
history of Mecca Caba all that. I have
never studied the ancient history of
Arabia. I have not done that. I have not
studied Islam. Okay? So I have zero
standing to comment on these issues. I
don't know about the history of I don't
know in any great detail the history of
Islam, the details of the history of
Islam. I don't know in any great detail
the history of Cabba and Mecca and all
that in any great detail and if there
are Indian connections I'm not aware of
them. We know that there was a pagan
temple. There were many maybe I don't
know how many lots of statues of pagan
gods. Yes, pre-Islabic gods. We know
that it's true. Um
there are reports of ancient 8,000 year
old temple in Saudi Arabia. I I I'm not
sure of that. So we know what what I can
tell you from the little knowledge I
have is that um this place was indeed a
pre-Islamic polytheistic place and there
apparently was a temple there with lots
of different de uh statues of gods and
goddesses which were all destroyed.
That's what I know. Was there a
connection with ancient Hinduism? Look,
Arabia is right across the western
Indian Ocean, the Sea of Saashtra.
we had in you know during the during the
Saraswati Hindu period of our history we
had trading posts there in Oman and so
on so we had a presence there so there
was definitely people-to-people
connection between the people of India
of the subcontinent and the people of
Arabia and Mesopotamia definite
people-to-people connections were there
right so was there a religious
connection also it is possible but I
can't say for sure
because I haven't studied it. All right,
that's all I can say. I'm sorry if I am
not able to answer your question, but my
knowledge is limited in these matters in
the matters of the history of Arabia and
the history of Islam. I my knowledge is
limited. So yeah, that's what that's all
I can tell you. All right, thank you
everybody for all the questions. I'm
going to end this here because in two
hours I have another live stream which
is about geopolitics. So I'm going to
end this here. Thank you so much
everybody for all the questions. We're
going to keep doing this. Hopefully
everybody gets to ask questions and get
their questions answered as long as the
questions are good and interesting to
me. Okay, so I'll end it over here.
Thank you so much everyone. Do check out
the books I'm publishing. Okay, I'm
writing it for you all. I'm not writing
a black holes books for scientists. I'm
writing it for the general public. All
right, I'm ending it here. Thank you so
much and I'll see you in the next live
stream. Take care. Bye-bye soon. See you
soon.